welcome from the magnets team let me remind
you that this seminar is about 25 minutes
presentation followed by 10 to 15 minutes
time for your questions and answers and there
is going to be time for catch up which is not
recorded and we welcome everybody to stay along
I am really happy and excited today to present
to present to you job learner who's going to
talk about using paramagnetism to evaluate
volcanic hazards um so please stay off um
the floors is yours go ahead okay um so yeah
thanks to everyone for for coming uh and I'm
gonna talk about a subject that that I find
interesting and I hope everyone else will um
and it's based on on some work I've done with with
a bunch of different colleagues um across a few
different places that I've worked from my PhD here
now so so from you know working at uh University
of Auckland in New Zealand Earth Observatory of
Singapore and now I'm at the national autonomous
University of Mexico uh in Mexico City and uh
most of the colleagues were either are or were
in in New Zealand um and are now in some other
places as well so what I want to talk about is
uh using paleomagnetism to look at volcanic
hazards and evaluate volcanic processes and
I think we in paleomagnetism we we use volcanic
rocks for for many of our studies and I'm sure
most of you who have used paleomagnetism
have used volcanic rocks at some point
um because they're good carriers of magnetic
data so they they contain magnetic mineralogy
typically uh and we can use them for pretty
much every every type of paleomagnetic study
whether it's looking at the Earth's interior or
geomagnetic reversals or many many things more
than than I've done a list uh but uh what I'm
interested in as as a sort of a volcanologist
that does paleomagnetism is turning it around
and and saying well as long as our volcanic rocks
record well paleomagnetic information let's use
those rocks instead to to look at the volcanoes
themselves and the processes that resulted
in in the formation of those volcanic rocks
and so what we can do with that uh with our our
paleomagnetic or Rock magnetic methods is we can
we can do absolute or relative dating um on on
eruption ages we can look at the emplacement
temperatures of of a variety of volcanic deposits
we can look at what direction was a volcanic flow
flowing in uh which we could maybe use to identify
where it came from if we don't already know uh
and we can look at uh maybe sediment cores to find
cryptotepra to potentially identify eruptions that
that we hadn't previously seen and so uh today
uh I'm going to be talking about how we can use
paleomagnetism uh through two different studies
to look at two very different volcanic hazards
uh that have a lot of things that are different
but important things in common that allows us to
study them with paleoism so we have lava flows
and we have pyroclastic density currents and so
we're gonna look at them so lava flows right
they're molten volcanic rock they're dense
um they're still uh in liquid form uh whereas
pyroclastic density currents are a mix of gas
and fragmented rock that comes out of an eruptive
Cloud that races down the side of the volcano so
speed we're looking at of these hazards is quite
different right so lava flows are typically slow
um most of the time we're looking at meters to
Second uh to even maybe meters per day if it's
mostly cool than moving quite slowly so this is
a hazard that most of the time you could walk
away from uh whereas pyroclastic density currents
or pdcs I'll probably call them many times during
the tuck uh are extremely test so up to over 100
meters per second so we're talking a hazard that
you can't even drive away from in most cases so
because of their their characteristics uh lava
flows are mostly dangerous to property uh they
can start fires they can generate explosions from
contact with water or or fuel uh so we're talking
about this kind of Hazard whereas pyroclastic
density currents are directly hazardous to people
so they're they're usually but not always fatal
um they can also damage buildings so they have
extremely high Dynamic pressure uh so so through
temperature and force they can cause extreme
damage but what they have in common is that
they're both high temperature hazards so both
of these hazards level flows and bdcs can be up
to over 800 Degrees which means that they heat
or reheat material that they come into contact
with and this is important because we use high
temperatures when we're doing paleomagnetic
experiments and we learn things about temperatures
and so we can combine those properties to to use
paleomagnetism to look at these hazards and so the
first thing that we're going to look at is can we
identify pdcs using paleomagnetism maybe when we
couldn't identify them in the field and so where
we're going to do that is New Zealand at an active
strata volcano called Mount taranaki uh so Mount
taranaki has about a hundred seventy thousand year
history of pretty much every main type of eruption
that that there is so it's had lava flows it's
had bbcs it's had lahars which are volcanic mud
flows so pdcs are a high temperature Hazard lahars
are our mud flows which means that they're usually
a low temperature Hazard um it's also had debris
Avalanches so so big scale collapse of the volcano
um it hasn't erupted in over 200 years but it's
been quite active over the past thousand years
and it's expected to erupt again sometime in the
in the future potentially in the next decades or
Century even um and so the question is if we look
at this this deposit in the picture at the bottom
um can we always differentiate between hot and
cold mass flow deposits in the field so if we
see these deposits that could be from different
types of volcanic flows particularly the hot PVCs
or the cold lahars in the field uh it's not always
so simple to to tell them apart especially because
remobilized material is exactly that it's it's
re-mobilized material of something that probably
used to be hot at some point and so it may look
exactly the same when you see it in a deposit
and the reason that we care about this is one of
the reasons is is for making Hazard Maps so it's
important for hazard planning to know where our
more dangerous and more safe areas around the
volcano in the case of an eruption and so in the
case of Matt taranaki this is an old hazard map
from maybe 20 years before we we did our study
uh and it was based on the fact that ddc's had
been identified to about 15 kilometers from the
volcano and basically that's your red circle and
so the red circle was your highest Hazard area
and saying if you're worried about pyroclastic
density currents that's the place where you need
to be worried about it and everything outside
that our colors indicating some kind of Lahar
or cold deposit thicking has been mapped much
further and we wanted to see if we're always
trying to improve Hazard Maps so people can
be better prepared in the case of interruption
and so what we did was we looked at some older
deposits from about 11 and a half thousand years
ago that had been up until our study considered to
be all the hard deposits right because they're
all past 15 kilometers they're all far away
um they're all these these water saturated
debris loads um that that were between 15
kilometers and the coast which is
25 kilometers or so from the volcano
uh and and these deposits in some places looked
like what our characteristics of large deposits
but in other places they had these characteristics
that are sometimes identified with with hotter
um pyroclastic density currents and so some
of those include an indurated deposit right
so the heat of the deposit uh causes it to be
much more more cohesive much more uh durable
um and bread crust bronze so they're basically
large chunks of of class of of a lava Dome or or
um or fragmented material and Interruption that
has a particular characteristic that's that's
typically associated with interruptive processes
and so we what we did uh was yeah we looked at
this area uh with different parts of this deposit
so some which could be lahars but some which might
have been hot and and we sampled these deposits
for failure magnetism so the way this works was
we sampled six locations um between that range
of 15 to 20 kilometers from The Source uh three
of those we did sort of traditional sites for the
method that I'm about to to outline so basically
we sampled a bunch of of class so so fist size
rocks or larger um from the same outcome and then
in five sites we we instead sampled directly The
Matrix because it was Consolidated enough that we
could we could take pieces of the Matrix like you
see in the picture on the right and we could sort
of put them in sampling cubes and and turn them
into cohesive samples and then cut them out of the
cube so we could use thermal demagnetization
to do Paleo magnetic experiments on them
so the way we measure and placement temperature
in a volcanic deposit is as I said right we
sample either a bunch of class so we take a
bunch of these rocks from the same location
or we sample directly The Matrix and so now I want
you to to imagine a little bit of volcano right so
we're going to imagine three possible scenarios at
the volcano that represent the types of deposits
we could find so imagine a volcano it erupts we
have this hot material coming out at the top of
the volcano and we have this pyroclastic density
current and it's it's really hot it's hotter than
our carry temperatures so let's say it's at least
580 or or 600 Degrees or hotter and it races down
the volcano this deposit altogether it it gets
to where it's going it's it's for this point
and it stops and it's still very hot and then it
all cools together right so it all cools in the
same place in the same magnetic field at the
same time and that means that if we come back
and resample it later however many years later we
would expect all of the material in that deposits
to have taken on the same paleomagnetic direction
single component and show us the same result
uh and that's what we will get if we
look at all our class to our Matrix
so now imagine the opposite scenario we have um we
have our hot material it's erupted it's in place
it all cools in the same place it all takes on
the same direction but then it moves again right
so it's it's water saturated or or for another
reason it moves further down the volcano we've
basically taken our directions that we're all the
same and we've physically reworked them physically
moved every single piece of this deposit and so
now if we sample this deposit later on we'd expect
to get a completely random set of directions
from our various classes or Matrix samples
okay and one more scenario is in the middle so
imagine we have a pyroclastic density current
that's either below carry temperature already
to start or imagine it's deposited and it cools
a little bit and then it moves again in this
case we'd expect to get a more complicated
result when we measure the samples we'd expect
to get at least at least two components and the
last component would be the component where
the material has all cooled together in the
same field and would show a consistent Direction
so we would see a consistent interaction at this
low temperature but at the higher temperatures
before the material moved we'd expect to see
that random alignment so we use that to to decide
how was our uh how are our deposits in place so
uh we got results from from all these different
sites and they mostly looked like this right so
we had as I said a high temperature component
and a low temperature component and you can see
in our high temperature component uh you you do a
Randomness test but I like this method because I
think most of the time you can even just you
could show this to to anyone and they would
usually agree with you by eye that the one on the
left is is pretty random alignment of quests of
daily magnetic directions on our stereo plot and
our our low temperature component on the right is
much more aligned and much more consistent and so
we did that on a variety of samples both Matrix
and class sites and we had basically mostly
similar results right we had two components
um one that was random at the higher temperature
before the material was in place and one at a low
temperature that was aligned after the material
was in place and what we do when that happens
is we can figure out even more precisely what was
going on what was the temperature and so the way
we did that was look we look at our our Vector
component plot our demagnetization plot and we
looked at the two components and the place
where there's a an obvious hopefully obvious
or sometimes not quite so obvious break between
our components is basically what we interpret to
be about our in placement temperature and so you
can see at least in the two on the right the break
between the two components is pretty clear and uh
and so that gives us the temperature on in this
one in the upper right of 400 110 degrees and in
the bottom right of 300 degrees and so what we had
across all of our sites was in seven of the eight
sites that we we had uh we had temperatures uh
ranging from 250 degrees to over 500 Degrees and
what that indicated to us was that these deposits
um at least the deposits we sampled were mostly
in place by a PVC and they weren't remobilized
deposits from from an earlier eruption that
that was smaller so what did we learn from
this about studying volcanoes with paleomag we
learned that this this deposit these deposits
um were actually in place not from from lahars
from reworked material but from PTC deposits
that were replaced at uh potentially a range of
temperatures but at least 250 degrees at a minimum
um and based on the deposit locations
and distances and the thicknesses of
the deposits where we found them this is more on
the volcanological side that it's probably in the
range of some of the larger eruptions that that
have been identified at this volcano and so so
it's important for the hazard because we're
not saying that this is going to happen in
every eruption that every eruption is going to
sort of send these these devastating pdc's all
the way to the coast but it is among the
worst case scenarios and so it's something
that's worth thinking about and so in 2021 the
civil defense of the region was was making new
Hazard material to to educate people who live
there and part of that was making a new map and
so what they did was they still have this High
Hazard area in the center because that's still
the most likely area for bdcs but now this is a
map of of just PDC Hazard and what they've done
is they've said okay now now there is some Hazard
that's worth considering um much further away
than we previously said and so this is a useful
application of the work we've done okay so lava
flows we're going to change track and and look at
a different study that's looking at lava flows uh
and so yeah as a reminder right lava flows can
be temperatures up to around a thousand degrees
Celsius so high heat again they redistribute heat
internally through conduction and convection and
uh and then the important part for for Paleo
magnetism for us is that they conduct heat into
adjacent materials so if they touch other stuff I
mean it's pretty obvious they they send the heat
into the other material that they're touching
or even uh if they're just near other materials
right through radiative they can also eat nearby
materials and so uh and two different extents
right so we see in this little cartoon something
explanatic on the right you see you have your lava
flow on the surface and and the heat is extending
into the ground under it to to different amounts
um and this is dependent on a variety of factors
so the lava and the substrate so whatever
is under the lava and and depending on
what type of lava we're talking about
they have different properties themselves
that affect how they they conduct and and
how the heat is transferred uh and then also
there's a number of lava flow characteristics
that are really important so how thick is the lava
flow over the material that that it's above uh
what's the flow rate so how much lava is coming
past uh what's the temperature of the lava flow
and uh and how long is this lava flow active
on top of the material it's over right so some
of these things are are intuitive the longer
the lava flow is hot above the material under
it the more the heat will will be able to
extend below and so why does this matter
so it matters the main the main reason that we're
interested in this is that it's a hazard to vary
in infrastructure so there are are some urban
areas that that are at risk to to uh lava flow so
there are um urban areas like uh
like Goma near near Congo or uh
or Auckland in New Zealand which is basically
built on an active volcanic field where
planning is being done in in the case of uh
potential lava flows in the city and cities
often have varied infrastructure right so there's
water pipes there's there's uh fiber lines there's
electrical lines and they're buried and if
there's lava flowing over that stuff we want to
know what's deep enough depth to bury this stuff
that that it's not going to be affected by the
Heat or or what are our different lava scenarios
depending on how much lava do we have what are
the chances that it affects the stuff underneath
it so so that's an important Hazard consideration
um there's some other other reasons as well
that that it's an important thing to study
okay so uh just to show sort of the properties of
of how how this reading uh affects the thermore
magnetization which a lot of you will will have
already seen these diagrams a million times but uh
basically uh our our sort of Baseline scenario
is that we have uh our material normal volcanic
material that's at high temperature uh and we
have our magnetic grains that are randomly aligned
we cool it down uh and we align all of our grains
in the same direction right that's that's standard
uh then some time passes and we have a magnetic
field that's that's significantly different enough
to tell the difference from our old magnetic field
and let's say we heat up that material in this
case let's say we heat it up all the way right um
we randomize our grains again because we're above
the carry temperature and we cool down again and
we will take on the direction of the new field so
this is this is pretty basic billiomagnetism and
let's say we we do that partially so if we heated
our our material back up only to uh 300 degrees
and um then we would we would over print the
magnetic Direction up to that temperature and
keep our old Direction above that temperature
okay so let's say we're looking at soils or
at least the way we've found it in soils and
and in this case we're assuming soils that are
are probably volcanically derived or soils that
that have some magnetic material in them right
because in order to to study the paleomagnetism
we need that uh but luckily we were working in
this study in New Zealand and Hawaii which which
have magnetically uh soils with Magnetic material
in them because they're volcanically derived so
again we have our magnetic field uh this time
we have a soil that is at ambient temperature
uh and and what we found is that soils typically
uh because they're just they're broken down
material from from from pre-existing material
they have a weak or or random Direction uh so
they are not showing struggle alignment typically
even if they have magnetic material in them if we
heat those soils up because they contain magnetic
material now we still have our random alignment
but we're above carry temperature and now if
we cooled them down they do take an alignment
um because of the magnetic material and it may not
be as strong as as a Basalt or or an endocyte or
another volcanic rock but it does exist and we
can measure it and and so this is the property
that we're going to use to to look at how much
heat spreads with the lava flows so the way we
do that is basically we imagine our lava flow and
it's flowing over some pre-existing substrate and
we imagine that once this lava flow is heated and
cooled the material um it's affecting stuff more
that's close to the lava flow right so it's going
to transfer the heat more into stuff that's close
and less into stuff that's far away or or next
to it and um and so you can see sort of just
through how I've shown these arrows we'd expect
to see this realignment of the magnetic material
uh more when it's close under the lava flow and
less when it's further away from the lava flow
and so the the obvious way to approach this is to
sample sequentially a profile uh perpendicular to
the lava flow so so for example below the level
flow then we continue to sample down to a depth
uh below the local flow and we would expect to
see different results in our different samples
so uh what did we do you can see from these
pictures on the right that the material we sampled
was quite different that was below the lava flows
and so we sampled the some uh score Abram that
was a human-made scoria berm that was below one
of the 2018 lava flows uh we sampled some baked
clay that was previously below lava flows in
the Auckland volcanic field in New Zealand
and uh as well in in the Auckland volcanic field
in New Zealand some baked soils that are currently
need a lava flow and so the samples as you can
see from those pictures were taken in different
ways so a core and then boxes or or just boxes
directly into the soil or in the case of our
baked Clays they were cohesive enough to to begin
with that we were able to just drill them directly
after after taking them back as hand samples
and so uh so again same as our previous study
we sort of Consolidated these samples and cut
them out of their boxes so we could use thermal
multi-magnetization uh and what we got was uh was
these results and so basically what we had in ours
um once we reach the the temperature at which they
started to unblock once we start to get our Real
Results was a single component of magnetization
all the way up to the uh the origin so basically
a single single heating all the way um to the
highest temperature we were able to eat so we
say that in our our different samples um and
I'll get into the interpretation in a second uh
another note these this is an example from um
alternating field demagnetization and for for
both of the methods that I'm showing today there's
there's stuff to be learned with with alternating
field demagnetization but just not quite as much
because the temperature is such an important thing
about what we're trying to understand the uh
the temperature steps that you get in a thermal
demagnetization procedure right using heat to
demagnetize our samples does get us more data
and important data that they just won't get with
the sort of Mila Tesla steps from from alternating
field demagnetization and so if you need to use
this it works but it's not quite as ideal right
um so the interpretation is uh that all of
our samples in in in this study that we were
able to get were were heated until at least the
maximum demagnetization temperature and so in
most of our samples we were able to heat them to
about 570 degrees until either they were mostly
demagnetized or in some cases because we had sort
of Consolidated these samples they they didn't all
survive terribly well until until we wanted them
to so um but the the caveat here is that that
this temperature was reached to the maximum
depth sample then in our study uh because of
the way the sites were we were only able to to
uh sample to a maximum depth of 21 centimeters
below the the deepest uh at the deepest site and
so what that means is that at in our case to at
least 21 centimeters uh our our samples were all
heated to above carry temperature by outflow and
so it with this method that means that sort of if
your samples are like call it saturated basically
if they're heated to above carry temperature
you can't get any kind of precise uh heating
temperatures and what that means is that there's
there's improvements for this method that will
get you more interesting results and the obvious
Improvement is sample to a deeper depth if you can
find a site where where the accessible material
beneath the flow is uh ideally probably more than
a meter or or even more of course depending
on on properties of the flow um and if you'd
expect that the deeper you sample um the more you
would expect to see uh your your component of of
stable Direction wouldn't go all the way to the
curated temperature you would have some random
element above that where uh where the magnetic
minerals have not been aligned by by reheating
um and the other way you can see that which I
didn't show but but you can see very easily if
you sample that uh is a control sample right so
you want to sample what's the the soil typically
light so you can compare it to uh to your your
samples that you're measuring and what the soil
is typically like uh is is this random weak
alignment but maybe your underlying material
could be another lava flow and if that's the
case you would expect to see a strong Direction
it would be interesting to then compare and see
if you have a strong stable Direction uh in the
direction of the original lava flow that is then
over printed to some amount by by the new lava
flow so in a sense it's basically a version of the
baked contact test where you're looking for the
overprint of the pre-existing material and then
of course as we found as our samples disintegrated
a bit and we're a bit hard to work with that it
I if you can find a site with with samples with
underlying material that that makes for good
samples uh it's going to mean that you're able
to sort of demagnetize them more fully as much
as you want to and ideally get the best results
so uh just to to summarize uh from these
two studies uh the the relationship between
paleomagnetism and temperature um means that this
works great in both directions so we can use our
volcanic rocks for all sorts of great paleomatic
studies about all sorts of things but we can
also turn it around and and really I think it's a
valuable method for looking at volcanic processes
um and especially uh even volcanic hazards
because many volcanic hazards uh part of
the reason there has to this is that they're
they're high temperature that's how they cause
their their damage or their injury um to a large
extent and so so it's an important aspect that
paleomag lets us study and paleomagnetism is
is a good proxy for temperature if we're using
thermal de negativization um because it has
these temperature steps it can get us this
resolution of temperature-based processes uh and
so yeah it can it can provide us good information
um for better understanding Hazard and and
impacts during past eruptions and that's a
really important thing in in planning for future
eruptions and mitigating future eruptions where
basically the more you know about these hazards
and the more you know about the history of of the
relevant volcano the uh the more the better you
can prepare the more you know what might happen
in the future so thanks thank you very much
Jeff uh let's give a big round of applause
um thank you so if there is any
question from the audience please
feel free to raise your hand or write
it in the chat I carried it out for you
yes Greg hi Jeff uh thanks very much for a really
good talk um I guess my question is not really
a scientific one and it's actually more of a
policy one I mean how I mean I don't know if
you've had any interactions with with some of the
local governments in these areas and the policy
makers and and the organizations responsible for
uh Hazard mitigation but I mean how how receptive
are these sort of people and organizations to
taking on board this kind of peri-magnetic data
and actually incorporating it into uh the
hazard assessments that that you publish
yeah so I'm I'm sure it depends on where you are
uh but in New Zealand I found it was it's they
they there's a very good and close relationship in
in most of the places with the volcanoes between
the the local councils and the universities and
the scientists and so yeah this this volcano
taranaki where I was working my my supervisor
had had a quite a long relationship with the
civil defense and he would go periodically every
year I think or more often to present relevant
results to them and um and so one year I like
with this this part that I presented here I I
went to the council and I presented them my my
stuff and yeah they seemed interested and then
yeah they are they're always working with the
universities for example when they they did this
this project last year to sort of update all
the hazard information they basically did they
worked with all the the cartographers and and the
scientists at the universities in New Zealand that
that work on this volcano to try to update that
and they do that in Auckland as well with the
volcanic field the council really works with and
funds a lot of relevant research and so I think
yeah the paleomagnetism I think as long as you you
put it in the context of of volcanology because I
think they're not necessarily at the council
level familiar with with paleo mag but if you
put it in the context of of how it's relevant
to the volcano I think they're very interested
um that helps because New Zealand is is small and
I think uh it's easier to have this relationship
so I don't know if it's probably not quite so
simple everywhere to get the ear of the the
local government or the national government
but um maybe in some places it is thank you
um is there any other questions from the audience
Greg Greg too Greg the second yeah I mean
this is a topic that I'm obviously um quite
interested in I've been I was kind of wondering
right when people are looking at at soils for
um you know period climate proxies and all sorts
and they do you know measurements with Magnetic
susceptibilities we heat the samples up and
and we tend to see this uh magnetic enhancement
um sort of formation of new magnetic minerals
when um when we hit them up in the lab uh do you
see evidence of this um um in some of your soil
samples that you're looking at and is there any
you know is there any extra information to be
gleaned about um the kind of temperatures you
know you can obviously see things are happening
above the security temperature that's kind of
then uh a bound it's a limit it doesn't actually
tell you exactly what the temperature was but
you know are there other chemical reactions
and things that you might be able to use to
um put other constraints on on temperatures
probably um so initially basically uh that
the first bits of study that we did before we sort
of figured out that you know came up with our way
to remove the the samples from their little
plastic boxes so we could actually eat them
um was basically just to look for for magnetic
enhancement and and or just the the Improvement
of the the strength of the signal sort of
and and using the alternating field and so it
already with that information it was enough
to to get a decent amount of information
maybe about the depth of the heating of course
you would then be missing sort of the precise
temperature information but um but yeah if
you took that and you you uh yeah come if
you if you have studies I mean I'm not I'm not
super familiar with studies of sort of magnetic
alteration and magnetic enhancement and and
what happens at different temperatures but
I would imagine with that information you could
you could use that to look at if it's you expect
to have a certain mineral formed or or change
in the mineralogy uh with eating to a certain
temperature I'm sure you could uh you could
add that onto the Paleo mag to look when you
get to higher temperatures where the Paleo mag
isn't getting you uh your information anymore
thank you
it's always very multi-disciplinary anyway
as an approach so um we we collaborate
with volcanologists but also geochemistry and
others right Jeff I mean usually a team effort
yeah but I like to see these methods combined
with with other methods I mean I think
a lot of volcanologists overlook paleo mag
because it's labor and you know it's it's
the sampling and the measurement is labor
intensive and so but I feel like a lot of
the time with volcanology studies it's really
simple to say oh let's just you know we'll add
the geochem to the paper because because we
have it and it's useful for people to know
I feel like that's something that sometimes
could be could be done with paleomatic why
not uh do enhance our study with with some
one of these methods with some some type
of paleomatic I think that can be done
a lot more than it is Maybe yeah thanks
um I don't know if there is any any
other question from the audience
I guess I have one well I have many sure that's
why we keep doing research on it because we
still have many questions exactly sure my uh my
question was regarding the study of the Anisa of
my medicine susceptibility uh when you apply
it on lahars and when you apply to pdcs that
you suspect they were Lars do you expect kind
of a different outcome from these two cases
uh so um oh sorry in terms of like how good your
AMS data could be out of these two cases yeah um
I mean so I guess the AMS with AMS we're talking
about a physical realignment right rather than
than the the alignment of the the remnants and so
I did a little bit of I didn't I didn't sort of do
enough of it to make a study out of it but I was I
did a little bit of AMS on on the pdc's uh just to
see and and I got what you would basically expect
which is aligned with with the flow Direction so
basically you get uh the at the point at which I
sampled them they were flowing over an extremely
low angle like two three degree slope and and then
so basically you get a almost flat you know an
almost horizontal uh direction of flow so it makes
sense at least um if you used it on the hearse I
haven't tried that uh what the deposits that I
knew for sure were cold and I would guess you'd
probably since it's a physical realignment I would
guess you'd probably get the same kind of result I
think you would it would physically align in the
in the flow Direction whatever that direction is
um I think with that it's interesting we were I
was trying to use it at some point and again I
didn't I didn't have really good AMS equipment so
I I wasn't uh for measuring so it wasn't wasn't
doing it super formally but we were looking at
hydrothermal deposits and the problem with them
also is they're not necessarily hot enough to
well but it's a physical realignment again we
were trying to figure out where were unknown uh
erective craters and so that I think would be
interesting more uh because if you could collect
the flow directions from a whole bunch of deposits
uh and they all seem to be coming from from
some unknown place it would be quite interesting
thank you thank you very much
um if there are no other questions maybe we can
just give Jeff another big round of applause
uh thanks thanks again for your talk and
I'm gonna be sharing a few slides left
so upcoming uh seminars we have second November
Joe Emmett from Florida 160 November Despina
condopolo from Thessaloniki in Greece and
we are solidity speakers for next year so
if you're interested to to give a seminar please
contact myself or any other member of the team
and please know that these uh seminars
together with the previous one can be found
on our YouTube channel that you're welcome
to like join watch or watch anytime you want
and yeah thank you very much for joining